## Michael Susz

Rindge, New Hampshire • https://linkedin.com/in/michaelsusz/

# Front End Developer & Team Lead

UX focused • Relationship Builder • Agile Practitioner

Front End Developer and Team Lead specializing in delivering rich applications and data visualization. Skilled at writing superior code, working with stakeholders, and brokering compromises. Advocate for web performance, usability and accessibility. Excels in ideation/iterative design sessions to improve user experience. Notable knowledge of and experience with Agile.

## **Core Competencies**

UI Development | Team Leader | Agile | Scrum Master | Accessibility | Cross Functional Collaboration Data Analytics | Project Management | Mentoring | Maintenance and Support | Design Systems

# **Professional Experience**

IBM 2021-CURRENT

#### Senior Front-End Developer, IBM Consulting

Contribute to a variety of client projects, from Application Development to Design Systems creation. Typically working in Agile methodology and using tech: HTML, CSS, Sass, JavaScript, Typescript, React, Sveltekit, Design Systems. Some GraphQL, React Native, Web Components.

IBM 2017 – 2021

## Front End Developer/Team Lead and Scrum Master, Cloud & Cognitive Solutions

Oversaw agile process, release planning, feature definition, and cross functional coordination. Responsible for coordinating product ideation, execution, and delivery. Integrated design systems into mature application. Accountable for code quality, performance, and accessibility.

- UI Technologies: HTML, CSS, Sass, React/Redux-Saga, Underscore, Jest, IBM's Carbon Design System
- DevOps tools/pipeline: GitHub Enterprise, Node, NPM, Express, Webpack, Jenkins, Travis, AWS EC2 & S3

# OPTUM TECHNOLOGIES / UNITED HEALTH GROUP UI Technical Lead

2014 - 2017

## or recilincal Leau

Led a team of HTML/CSS developers, working in concert with Angular JavaScript developers and Java API developers. Created web and responsive mobile apps for management of healthcare programs and benefits. Ensured code compatibility, accessibility and performance.

- Technologies: Angular 1.5, HTML, CSS, Sass, Less-CSS, Adobe Experience Manager (AEM)
- DevOps pipeline: git, Jenkins, Redhat Openshift

MICHAEL SUSZ PAGE 2

SQUAREDESIGN 2007 – 2014

#### **UI and CMS Consultant**

Consulted and worked on highly detailed UI implementations and WordPress CMS development. Built websites and advised clients incl. Evernote, Sony, Monster.com, Kronos, Fidelity, SpringPad, Deloitte, and Harvard Pilgrim

UI Technologies: HTML, CSS, Sass, JavaScript, jQuery, PNG and SVG sprites & optimization

• CMS/Backend: WordPress API, Theme, and Plugin development with publishing workflow/WP Admin customizations, MySQL

WASHINGTON MUTUAL 2002 – 2007

## Programmer/Analyst Sr. I

UI focused developer in Online Banking. Collaborated with usability and marketing to conceive and implement a pattern library of re-usable .NET components. Brought WaMu Online Banking product into accessibility compliance. Spearheaded a UI design as a version-able asset of projects, allowing individual apps to use new patterns without requiring widespread regression testing.

- Front-end technologies: Semantic HTML/CSS, raw JavaScript, WAI, Section 508.
- Back-end technologies: Asp.NET/C#, Classic ASP, XML/XSLT, Microsoft CMS Server

REAL NETWORKS 2001 – 2002

#### Front End / Back End Developer

Performed front end and back end development for client websites using HTML, CSS, PHP, and Roxen/RXML as well as Linux server setup and maintenance. Shifted to semantic markup and web-standards based development.

INTUIT 2000 – 2001

#### **UI Developer**

Assigned as a web engineer/HTML expert on a cross-disciplinary team in the User-Centered Design division focused on a project to help design, usability test, iterate, and develop an online CMS to power small-business websites.

# **Technologies & Tools**

HTML / Semantic Markup, CSS, Sass, Less-CSS, CSS-in-JS
Vanilla JavaScript, React, JSX, jQuery (some Angular, some React Native, some Typescript)
Jenkins CI, npm, AWS, Netlify, Docker, and OpenShift
Photoshop, Illustrator, Omnigraffle, Sketch App, Create & Optimize PNG and SVG Graphics
Accessibility Including WCAG-2.0, Aria Roles and Section 508 Compliance
Project Management Tools: Trello, Jazz, Jira, Rally, and ZenHub

## **Education & Professional Development**

#### **Education**

Took Coursework in IT, Business Administration, Economics, Architecture/Architectural Engineering, and Psychology at Edmonds Community College, SUNY Buffalo, and Wentworth institute of Technology

#### Trainings

IBM Trained as a Participant, Facilitator (Scrum Master), and Advocate (Teacher) in Agile. Familiarity with National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) Controls for ISO27k Certification

## **Public Speaking**

WordCamp Boston: Presented Sessions: *Decisions, Decisions* About Project Inception and Organization |

WordPress Theme Construction | Lightning Talk -- Short Codes: Pain Free Magic

BarCamp Manchester: SASS – Syntactically Awesome Style Sheets | Lessons Learned from Full-Time Freelancing